# Jessica R. Conrad

Curriculum Vitae

University of Michigan
Department of Mathematics
530 Church St
Ann Arbor, MI 48109
707.799.9564
Signification jrconrad@umich.edu
http://jessicarconrad.github.io/

# Summary of Qualifications

Ms. Conrad works on developing and analyzing mathematical, computational, and statistical models for the spread of infectious diseases such as smallpox, Ebola, dengue, Zika, Chikungunia, malaria, Chagas, influenza, and SARS-CoV. She is interested in research problems pertaining to dynamical systems and epidemiology, particularly modeling emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases and determining effective control strategies to halt disease transmission.

#### Education

- ${\rm Jan}\ 2020$   $\ {\rm PhD}$  in Applied & Interdisciplinary Mathematics and Scientific Computing,
  - Present University of Michigan, Advisor: Dr. Marisa Eisenberg, GPA: 3.73.
- Jan 2016 Master of Science in Public Health, Biostatistics, Tulane University, Advisors:
- May 2018 Dr. John Lefante and Dr. Latha Rajan, Public Health Analysis: An Assessment of Polynomial Distributed Lag in Mosquito-Born Disease Risk Modeling, GPA: 3.97.
- Aug 2013 Bachelor of Science, Mathematics, Tulane University, Advisors: Dr. James (Mac)
- Dec 2016 Hyman and Dr. Claudia Herrera, Thesis: Mitigating Chagas Disease: Fighting an Infection with an Infection, GPA: 3.88.
- Aug 2013 Bachelor of Science, Public Health, Tulane University, GPA: 3.88.
- Dec 2016

# Grants and Fellowships

- 2019 Clare Boothe Luce Fellowship
  - Michigan Institute for Computational Discovery and Engineering Fellowship
- 2015 Louisiana Supervised Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE) Grant
- Select Travel SIAM-SEAS Conference (2018), Penny Jessop Travel Grant (2017), Student Government
  - Grants Association Grant (2017), ICMA-VI Conference (2017), SAMSI Undergraduate Workshop (2017), Newcomb-Tulane College Travel Grant (2015), SACNAS First Time Travel Grant (2015), Research Training Group Workshop on Agent-Based Modeling (2015)

# Competitive Awards

- 2020 Los Alamos National Laboratory 2020 Spot Award for Emergency COVID Response
- 2020 Los Alamos National Laboratory 2020 Spot Award for Outstanding Performance
- 2018 Los Alamos 2018 Post-Masters Internship in Infectious Disease Modeling
- 2017 Tulane 34 Award
  - NSF's SEES Fellows: Modeling for sustainability in a changing environment
- 2013 Presidential Scholar Award for Tulane University Air Force Type II Four Year Scholarship

# Professional Experience

May 2020 – **Graduate Research Assistant**, *Theoretical Division*, *T-6*, Los Alamos Naitonal Lab-Aug 2021 oratory (LANL), I continued on the project developing a database and models for 30 diseases of interest to the Defense Threat Reduction Agency, specific focus on emergency COVID modeling and response efforts.

PI: Dr. Paul Fenimore; Role: Research Assistant

July 2018 – **Postmasters Research Assistant**, Theoretical Division, T-6, Los Alamos Naitonal Aug 2019 Laboratory (LANL), I developed a database and models for 30 diseases of interest to the Defense Threat Reduction Agency; conducted anomaly analysis for driving factors of mosquitos carrying West Nile Virus prevalence in the United States through internal LANL funding; and collected clinical, syndromic, and genomic data for the seasonal flu; also conducted preliminary research in accuracy and prediction of influenza diagnosis in clinical settings for the Department of Homeland Security.

PI: Dr. Paul Fenimore; Role: Research Assistant

Jan – Dec **Public Health Analysis Masters Thesis**, School of Public Health and Tropical 2017 Medicine, Tulane University, I constructed a polynomial distributed lag model under different truncation lag criteria (simple, marginal, and minimized AIC) to predict reported dengue cases in Ceará, Brazil. I determined which predictors were most significant for dengue transmission in Ceará.

Advisor(s): Dr. John Lefante Dr. Latha Rajan; Role: Research Assistant

May – Dec Graduate Research Assistant, SEES Fellows, New Mexico Consortium and LANL, I 2017 processed and analyzed raw data from climate, satellite imagery, Google Health Trends, Twitter, demographic information, and reported Dengue fever case counts in Brazil; generated ARMA prediction models in R for future dengue incidence from provided data streams; created database to store raw data using MySQL for easier data access and manipulation; and culminated in poster talk, "Using Satellite Imagery and Internet Data for Dengue Surveillance in Brazil." I received funding through SEES Fellows: Modeling for sustainability in a changing environment: emerging infectious diseases.

PI: Dr. Carrie Manore; Role: Research Assistant

Jan 2017– **Graduate Teaching Assistant**, Department of Public Health, Tulane University, I May 2018 mentored and tutored 60 students per semester of the undergraduate "The Cell, the Individual, and the Community" course. This including preparing teaching materials before class, organizing course records, and grading quizzes, as well as providing tutoring assistance outside of class hours.

Professor: Dr. Latha Rajan; Role: Teaching Assistant

Jan – Dec Undergraduate Research Assistant, Honors Thesis, Tulane University, I researched 2016 theoretical mitigation strategies for Chagas disease in the USA using deterministic Susceptible-Infected-Removed (SIR) modeling techniques; programmed Matlab to research host-vector competing infection model; generated comprehensive project technical report in LaTex; and presented a final paper and poster, "Mitigating Chagas Disease: Fighting an Infection with an Infection." In addition, I conducted field research collecting data on Chagas prevalence in the greater New Orleans area.

Advisor(s): Dr. James Hyman and Dr. Claudia Herrera; Role: Research Assistant

May – Aug Undergraduate Research Assistant, Mathematical and Theoretical Biology Institute 2015 (MTBI), Arizona State University, I conducted research on incentivizing reform programs in the Louisiana prison system, created a compartmental model and analysis using Matlab, Maple, and Mathematica programming, and culminated in paper, presentation, and poster talk titled "Minimizing recidivism by optimizing profit: a theoretical case study of incentivized reform in a Louisiana prison".

Advisor(s): Dr. Christopher Kribs and Dr. Benjamin Morin, Role: Research Assistant

Aug 2014 - Undergraduate Research Assistant, Mathematical Modeling of Biological Systems, May 2015 Tulane University, I published a paper, "Modeling the Impact of Behavior Change on the Spread of Ebola." I constructed epidemiological models using SIR techniques to summarize the impact of behavior change on Ebola incidence rates during the 2014 West Africa epidemic; compared results to stochastic model; developed analytical and numerical simulations to solve linear and nonlinear differential equations; and received a Louisiana Supervised Undergraduate Research Experience grant to fund research project. PI: Dr. James Hyman, Role: Research Assistant

Sep – Dec Smoke Free Ban Needs Assessment Coordinator, Louisiana Public Health Insti-2014 tute (LPHI), Tulane University, I conducted a needs assessment of New Orleans bar owners for LPHI, produced a literature review on the financial impact of smoking bans on bars and clubs, and reported results to LPHI to be used in the development of government policy, the Smoke Free Ban.

Advisor(s): Dr. Elisabeth Gleckler, Role: Needs Assessment Coordinator

## Selected Activities

Associations

Professional Rotary International, Rotary Club of New Orleans Riverbend, New Orleans, LA, An international service organization that provides humanitarian service to advance goodwill and peace around the world (2018).

> Role: Volunteering through Rotary since January 2014. Currently works with the Rotary Youth Exchange program as a Local Youth Exchange Coordinator

> Delta Omega National Honorary Society, Eta Chapter of Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, Public health honorary society for accredited schools and programs of public health. (2018).

> Omicron Delta Kappa Honors Fraternity, Circle of Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, National leadership honor society in the United States. (2017).

> Role: Served as President of the Tulane Circle from Jan.-Dec. 2017. Organized and coordinated advisory board meetings with Tulane administrators

> Rotaract, Rotaract of Tulane, New Orleans, LA, A service, leadership, professional and community service organization sponsored by Rotary International. (2014).

> Role: Founding member of the Rotaract at Tulane club. Served as President from July 2016 – July 2017. Organized volunteer events with over 30 organizations in the New Orleans area and abroad, including transportation, event details, and recruitment of volunteers for each event, and received \$2000 grant funding for community outreach in Kisumu, Kenya, for a water well project

Volunteer Refugee Health Program of the New Mexico Department of Health, Santa Fe, Activities NM, (2018-19).

> Role: Organized joint database for clinical and mental health information on refugees in New Mexico, and analyzed data from 2013-2018 for a 5-year retrospective EpiReport on the status of programs offered by the Refugee Health Program.

> Graduate Student Government Association Networking Subchair, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, (2017-18).

> Role: Solely planned networking event with the aid of SGA for students of the Tulane School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine (SPHTM) for 150 guests with \$6000 budget, and organized hotel contract and space, contacted alumni and students, and managed the budget for the Preceptor Thank You and Networking event.

Diversity Committee Member, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, (2017-18). Role: Served on graduate school diversity committee to improve student life.

President, Academic Tutoring for Roots of Music, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, (2014-15).

Role: Provided academic tutoring assistance to elementary and middle school students, supervised and coordinated transportation of volunteers to and from the tutoring site 4 days a week, and coordinated with the director of Roots of Music to create fun outdoor events for tutors and students.

Other Residential Advisor, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, (2015-17).

Positions Role: Managed 70 residents, including conflict resolution, resource connections, and life advice, worked with a wide range of students from undergraduate sophomores to Masters students, and organized programs to meet individual needs including community integration and mental health.

#### Invited Presentations

- 2021 Seminar Speaker, **AIM Student Seminar**, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan (September 15)
- 2020 Seminar Speaker, **AIM Student Seminar**, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan (October 30)
  - Guest Speaker for Class, **COMM 307: Social Networks**, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan (September 30)
- 2019 Workshop Speaker, **Workshop on Modeling the Spread of Infectious Diseases**, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana (February 22)
  - Guest Speaker for Class, **SPHU 1010: Introduction to Public Health**, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana (February 22)
- 2018 Seminar Speaker, Michigan Institute for Data Science Seminar, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan (September 27)
- 2016 Seminar Speaker, **Applied Mathematics Seminar**, Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York (October 28)

Private Presentation Speaker, **Ministry of Education of El Salvador**, San Salvador, El Salvador (February 24)

Conference Speaker, **Primer Congreso Internacional de Modelaje Matematico**, La Universidad de Francisco Gavidia, San Salvador, El Salvador (February 23)

## Contributed Presentations

2018 Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics, **42nd SIAM Southeastern Atlantic** Sectional Conference, Chapel Hill, North Carolina

Seminar Speaker, **CNLS Summer Talk Series**, Center for Nonlinear Studies (CNLS), Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, New Mexico

Scientific Computing Around Louisiana, SCALA 2018, Baton Rouge, Louisiana

2017 American Geophysics Union 2017 AGU Fall Meeting, New Orleans, Louisiana

American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene, **2017 ASTMH Annual Meeting**, Baltimore, Maryland

International Conference on Mathematical Modeling and Analysis of Populations in Biological Systems, **2017 ICMA-IV Conference**, Tuscon, Arizona

Seminar Speaker, **CNLS Summer Talk Series**, Center for Nonlinear Studies (CNLS), Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, New Mexico

2015 Society for the Advancement of Chicanos and Native Americans in Science 2015 SAC-NAS National Conference, Washington, D.C.

Tulane School of Science and Engineering, SSE Research Day, New Orleans, Louisiana

## **Publications**

Book [1] Conrad, J. R., Xue, L., Dewar, J., & Hyman, J. M. "Modeling the Impact of Behavior Chapters Change on the Spread of Ebola." Mathematical and Statistical Modeling for Emerging and Re-emerging Infectious Diseases. (2016) Springer.

Conference Proceedings

- [1] Conrad, J. R., Ziemann A., Refeld, R., Parikh, N., Siraj, A., Generous, N., Del Valle, S., Fairchild, G., & Manore, C. "Understanding polynomial distributed lag models: truncation lag implications for a mosquito-borne disease risk model in Brazil." Algorithms, Technologies, and Applications for Multispectral and Hyperspectral Imagery XXV. (2019) International Society for Optics and Photonics.
- [2] Ziemann, A., Fairchild, G., Conrad, J., Manore, C., Parikh, N., Del Valle, S., and Generous, N. "Predicting Dengue Incidence in Brazil Using Broad-Scale Spectral Remote Sensing Imagery." IGARSS 2018-2018 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium. (2018) IEEE.

Technical

- [1] Conrad, J. R., Guan, L., and Geneus, C. "Parameters Estimation, Identification Reports and Uncertainty Quantification for Epidemic Models." (2018) Tulane University.
  - [2] Conrad, J. R.. "Public Health Analysis: An Assessment of Polynomial Distributed Lag in Mosquito-Born Disease Risk Modeling." (2018) Tulane University.
  - [3] Conrad, J. R.. "Honors Thesis: Mathematical Analysis for a Model to Control Chagas Disease: Fighting as Infection with an Infection." (2017) Tulane University.
  - [4] Hamins-Puertolas, M., Conrad, J. R., Islas, G., Bossogo-Egoume, A., Kribs, C., and Morin, B. "Minimizing recidivism by optimizing profit: a theoretical case study of incentivized reform in a Louisiana prison." (2015) Mathematical and Theoretical Biology Institute.
  - [5] Conrad, J. R., Hajmurad, F., Patel, N., Reddy, A., and Shukla, A. "Needs Assessment: The Louisiana Institute of Public Health Tobacco Free Living Campaign." (2014) Tulane University and the Louisiana Public Health Institute.

Pre-prints

- [1] Shutt, D. P., Goodsman, D. W., Hemez, Z. J. L., Conrad, J. R., Xu, C., Osthus, D., Russel, C., Hyman, J. M., Manore, C. A. "A Process-based Model with Temperature, Water, and Lab-derived Data Improves Predictions of Daily Mosquito Density." (2021) Journal of Medical Entomology.
- [2] Mourant, J. R., Wilding, K., Conrad, J. R., Miner, J. C., Atchley, A. L., Fenimore, P. W. "EpiGrid: Consistent parameterization of three diseases using a single model." (2021) *PLoS ONE*.
- [3] Manore, C., Fairchild, G., Ziemann, A., Parikh, N., Kempfert, K., Martinez, K., Castro, L., Osthus, D., Siraj, A., Conrad, J., Generous, N., Del Valle, S. "Unlocking the Predictive Power of Heterogeneous Data to Build an Operational Dengue Forecasting System." (2020) Royal Society.

### Proficiencies

Computer R, Python, LaTex, SAS, SQL, Matlab, Mac OS, Windows

Skills

Languages Spanish (Conversational)

Professional Grant writing, mentorship, event planning, fundraising, disaster relief, media production

# Selected Media Coverage

2010 Michigan Institute for Computational Discovery & Engineering, Introducing the new Clare Boothe Luce Graduate Fellows at the University of Michigan, 24 June 2019.

2017 New Mexico Consortium, Student Research Seeks to Predict Dengue Fever Outbreaks, 5 December 2017.

Scientific American, Forecasting Outbreaks-1 Image at a Time, 10 Aug 2017.

Tulane New Wave, The Power of Tulane - Jessica Conrad, 13 July 2017.

Tulane New Wave, 2017 grad applies math to track Ebola outbreak, 28 Apr 2017.

#### **Hobbies**

Salsa dancing instructor, Hiking, Skiing, Karate instructor

## References

### Marisa Eisenberg, Ph.D., M.S.

Associate Professor

Epidemiology, Complex Systems, and Mathematics Departments, University of Michigan

Email: marisae@umich.edu, Phone: (734) 763-2991

Dr. Eisenberg is my PhD advisor.

#### James "Mac" Hyman, Ph.D.

Evelyn and John G. Phillips Distinguished Professor

Mathematics Department, Tulane University

Email: mhyman@tulane.edu, Phone: (504) 862-3433

Dr. Hyman was my undergraduate mathematics advisor and headed two of my research projects, including my undergraduate thesis.

#### Carrie Manore, Ph.D.

Scientist

Information Systems and Modeling, LANL

Email: cmanore@lanl.gov, Phone: (541) 207-7969

Dr. Manore is the PI for the research project investigating driving factors for mosquitos and West Nile.

#### Paul Fenimore, Ph.D.

Scientist

Theoretical Biology and Biophysics, LANL

Email: paulf@lanl.gov, Phone: (505) 665-7744

Dr. Fenimore is the PI for the research developing a universal model for 30 diseases of interest to the Defense Threat Reduction Agency.